<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lawfulnes of the late passages of the Army (especially of the grounds laid downe for their justification in their late declarations of June 14. 1647.) / Examined by one who hath long beene a friend to the Army, and desires satisfaction.</title>
            <author>One who hath long beene a friend to the Army.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88803</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L647</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E394_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201626</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862126</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862126</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114275</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88803)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114275)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 62:E394[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lawfulnes of the late passages of the Army (especially of the grounds laid downe for their justification in their late declarations of June 14. 1647.) / Examined by one who hath long beene a friend to the Army, and desires satisfaction.</title>
                  <author>One who hath long beene a friend to the Army.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeer 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 28".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Expulsion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Impeachments --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114275:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LAWFULNES OF THE LATE PASSAGES OF THE ARMY (Eſpecially of the Grounds laid downe for their JVSTIFICATION in their late DECLARATIONS of <hi>June</hi> 14. 1647.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EXAMINED</hi> by one who hath long beene a Friend to the ARMY, and deſires Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Yeer 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:114275:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:114275:2"/>
            <head>The Lawfulneſſe of the late Paſſages of the Army, eſpecially of the grounds laid down for their Juſtification in their late Declaration of <hi>June 14, 1647.</hi> examined by one that hath long been a Friend to the Army, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires ſatisfaction.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the late Declaration from the Army, of <hi>June</hi> 14, 1647, had given ſatisfaction to all their friends (as it ſeemed to promiſe in the firſt line) I ſhould then have been ſilent, who have ever (untill ſome of their late proceedings) not onely had the Army in great eſteem and honour, but have ſtudied, and andeavoured (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my abilities and place) to be ſerviceable to them: But now all my glorying in them is turned into ſhame, and all my prayers and praiſes to God for them, into mourning and aſtoniſhment, To ſee that under the Generalls notions and colours of Gods glory, and good intentions to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114275:3"/>
and Peace of the people of this Nation, the late acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and practices of the Army in diſobeying and oppoſing the Parliament (if perſiſted in) will appear to be contrary to the Laws of God, and the Kingdom, and to their duty, truſt, and ingagement to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> by whoſe Commiſſion, onely, they are an Army; and are but a tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous number of men, when they act, or do any thing that is not in order too, or within the limits of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, which I take to be the utmoſt bounds of their calling as an Army: And when any man (or number of men) ſtep out of their calling, or (if in their calling) run out into by and unwarrantable wayes, they can upon no good grounds either look for protection, or expect a bleſſing; and however ſuch proceedings (being backt with policy and power) may have ſucceſſe at preſent, yet they are ſure to be <hi>bitterneſſe in the end.</hi> Therefore I ſhall ever wonder at any, who (if they have good aims and intentions) will go the devils high-way to them, becauſe (it may be) it ſeems to be over at next. For my part, I will not judge that the Army have evil ends; but being altogether unſatisfied with their way, and with all they ſay in the defence of it, which coming from the Army in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and not from any particular perſon, or number of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, from whom I might have defired private ſatisfaction; and being exceedingly oppreſſed with the ſence of the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to God, the ſcandall (if not the ruine) to Religion, the inſultings of the enemies to the Parliament, and the great danger threatned to the whole Kingdom, all eminent if the Army ſhould perſiſt in their preſent courſe: I could have no peace within my ſelf, untill I had in this plain ſtyle (fitteſt for a mournfull Subject) declared the grounds of my disſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, hoping that for the future the Army will either ſubmit to their lawfull and undoubted Governours, or ſhew better cauſe to the contrary then any I can yet finde in their publike Declarations and reſolutions. And that I may not wrong them in repetition, or darken their reaſons, I have ſet down at large in the margent all I can finde of theirs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this point.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:114275:3"/>
            <q>
               <p>Nor will it now (we hope) ſeem ſtrange or unreaſonable to rationall and honeſt men, who conſider the conſequence of our preſent caſe, to their own and the Kingdoms, (as well as our) future concernments in point of Right, Freedom, Peace, and ſafety, if (from a deep ſenſe of the high conſequence of our preſent caſe, both to our ſelves (in future) and all other people) we ſhall, before dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding, proceed in our own and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms behalf, to propound and plead for ſome proviſion for our and the Kingdoms ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and future ſecurity, in relation to thoſe things, eſpecially conſidering that we were not a meer mercenary Army bired to ſerve any arbitrary power of a State, but called forth and conjured by the ſeverall De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations of Parliament, to the defence of our own and the peoples Rights and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; And ſo we took up Arms in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and conſcience to thoſe ends, and have ſo continued them, and are reſolved accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your firſt juſt deſires in your Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſuch principles as we have received from your frequent Informations, and our own common ſenſe, concerning thoſe our fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Rights and Liberties, to aſſert and vindicate the juſt power and Rights of this Kingdom in Parliament for thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ends premiſed against all arbitrary power, violence, and oppreſſion, and against all particular parties or intereſts whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. The ſaid Declarations ſtill directing us to the equitable ſenſe of all Laws and Constitutions, as diſpenſing with the very letter of the ſame, and being ſupreme to it, when <pb n="6" facs="tcp:114275:4"/> the ſafety and preſervation of all is concerned; And aſſuring us that all authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is fundamentally ſeated in the Office, and but miniſterially in the Perſons. Neither do or will theſe our proceedings (as we are fully and in conſcience perſwaded) amount to any thing not warrantable before God and men; being, thus far, much ſhort of the common proceedings in other Nations, to things of an higher nature then we have yet appeared to; and we cannot but be ſenſible of the great complaints that have been made to us gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in the Kingdom from the people where we march, of Arbitrarineſſe and Injustice, to their great and inſupportable oppreſſions.</p>
               <p>And truly ſuch Kingdoms as have accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both to the Law of Nature and Nations appeared to the vindication and defence of their juſt Rights and Liberties, have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded much higher, as our brethren of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who in the first beginning of theſe late differences aſſociated in covenant, from the very ſame grounds and principles (having no viſible form, either of Parliament or King to countenance them) And as they were therein juſtified and protected by their own and this Kingdom alſo, ſo we juſtly ſhall expect to be.</p>
               <p>We need not mention the States of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> the <hi>Portugals</hi> and others, all proceeding upon the ſame principles of right and freedom; And accordingly the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament hath declared it no reſiſting of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistracy, to ſide with the juſt principles and Law of Nature and Nations, being that Law upon which we have aſſisted you, and that the Souldiery may lawfully hold the hands of that Generall <pb n="7" facs="tcp:114275:4"/> who will turn his Canon againſt his Army on purpoſe to deſtroy them, the Seamen the hands of that Pilot, who wilfully runs the ſhip upon a rock, (as our brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> argued,) And ſuch were the proceedings of our Anceſtors of famous me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, to the purchaſing of ſuch Rights and Liberties, as they have enjoyed through the price of their blood, and we (both by that and the latter blood of our dear Friends, and fellow Souldiers with the hazard of our own) do now lay chain unto.</p>
               <p>Nor is that ſupreme end, (the Glory of God) wanting in theſe caſes, to ſet a price upon all ſuch proceedings of righteouſneſſe and justice, it being one Witneſſe of God in the world, to carry on a Testimony againſt the injustice and unrighteouſneſſe of men, and againſt the miſcarriage of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, when corrupted or declining from their primitive and originall glory.</p>
            </q>
            <p>In anſwer where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I muſt affirm, that, although as particular Engliſh men you may peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or plead for what you think makes for the right, freedom, peace, and ſafety of your ſelves, or of the Kingdom; yet you cannot do it as an Army, for that relates only to thoſe uſes (for which it was made) limited within its Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>For your affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you are not a mercenary Army, I will not ſpend time to diſpute it, yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one ſees you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt much upon your wages, wherewith the Scripture char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth Souldiers (that would be ſaved) to be content, <hi>Luk.</hi> 3. 14.</p>
            <p>For what you ſpeak of the arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry power of a State, and of violence, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, particular parties, and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114275:4"/>
if you apply it to the preſent caſe, to juſtifie your not obeying the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it ſignifies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing) then I muſt ſay it is exceeding unjuſt when you do not inſtance in any one action wherein they are willingly guilty of any ſuch charge. It is true that thoſe who have a legiſlative power cannot have an alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether limited pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; but that is no more in this, then in all Parliaments; And that ſo long as the calamities of the times did neceſſitate Armies, there muſt needs be burdens laid upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, even to more then ordinary preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: but was that the Parliaments fault? or thoſe that did oppoſe them? And that thoſe bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and preſſures muſt ſtill be kept up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people, is it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114275:4"/>
the fault of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that will not disband?</p>
            <p>For that you ſay you were called out by Declarations to the defence of your own, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Rights, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties; And that you (as an Army) will aſſert and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the juſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and rights of this Kingdom in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied but the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (to whom it belongs) having judged that the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces raiſed by the King, were to invade the people Rights, and Liberties, and the juſt Power and Rights of this Kingdom in Parliament, did publiſh it in Declarations, and thereupon did raiſe both you and ſeverall other Armies to oppoſe and reſiſt thoſe Forces: But how theſe Declarations give you a right to judge what theſe Liberties, juſt Power, or Rights are, either of the Parliament, or people, is (I think) paſt all humane underſtanding to conceive, neither the Laws of God, nor the Laws of the Kingdom having made you Judges, nor ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving put any of the weights or meaſures of Juſtice on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of others into your hands; you can onely do it by the length of your Swords, which can be no good Standard, for it will ſtill be liable to alteration when a longer Sword comes: And when the people of this Kingdom have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood and conſidered this, it is not likely that they will leave
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114275:5"/>
the ſettled courſe of Law, and Juſtice in the known Courts of the Kingdom, to be judged by any one that can raiſe the greateſt tumult; which muſt needs follow, if they allow this Army, (ſuppoſe it 14000 men to be Judges now) then any 150000 in the kingdom may judge the Army, and a greater number judge them <hi>ad Infinitum:</hi> by which it doth appear that the Army making themſelves Judges in theſe caſes, doth overthrow and take away the Ordinance of God and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy; then which amongſt men, I cannot imagine what is a greater impiety.</p>
            <p>Beſides their refuſing to obey the Parliament (under whoſe Command they are, or ought to be) is againſt many parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular precepts and directions in the Word of God, as you <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 10. <hi>Jud. v.</hi> 8, 11.</note> may finde them laid down in the Margent.</p>
            <p>For the great Complaints that have been made to you, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it were falſe that is reported (as I have cauſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve) that men are ſent from the Armie to get hands to Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions unto themſelves, thereby to draw the eyes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple after them; yet I doe conceive ſuch Petitions ought not to be received by any who either by Proteſtation or Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant have ſworne to mean the Juſt power and priviledges of Parliament, to whom of right it doth belong to heare and determine all the grievances of the People not remediable in other ordinary Courts of Juſtice; and there they may be heard without the forceable recommendation of an Army; who although they thruſt on thoſe things that upon ſerious debate have been rejected as prejudiciall to the Publique, yet it will be in vaine to thoſe who doe truely make conſcience of their duties; for they will not be frighted into other mens fancies againſt their own judgements. Yet if the Armie will give incouragement unto ſuch Petitions, and ſo ſet up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as a new Tribunall, I beleeve they ſhall have worke in all places where they come; for there, men will be glad to doe that which may pleaſe them, although they had no cauſe of complaint.</p>
            <p>For the examples of <hi>Scotland, Netherlands, Portugals,</hi> and ſome proceedings in this Parliament, which you urge for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114275:5"/>
your warrant, I muſt anſwer in generall, that preſidents are poor proofs to juſtifie actions, and if admitted, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo bad that might not obtain ſuch a juſtification: it is a warrant from ſome Law that muſt make every action law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Yet all thoſe inſtanced in, comes far ſhort of your caſe, for it can be ſaid of none of them, That they acted ſupream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by their own power, having no Civill power or Magiſtrate to declare with them, or for them: And although my buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be not to ſearch into the grounds, or proceedings upon which other Nations have taken up Arms; yet, being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to it, I muſt clear the miſapplication to <hi>Scotland,</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to our ſelves in this Kingdom. For <hi>Scotland,</hi> I may affirm, that although in the beginning of theſe late diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences (to which the Declaration doth refer) the common people there, did firſt oppoſe thoſe illegall impoſitions, and innovations, ſtrongly endeavoured to be thruſt upon them; yet they did not enter into any Covenant, nor raiſe any Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, untill the Civill powers in that Kingdom had declared it to be juſt, and according to the Laws and Cuſtoms of that Nation; nor did their Armies act but by the ſame ſupream Authority and Command: And although both the firſt and laſt Armies raiſed in that Kindom, were ſtrong, and knew that the State had no other conſiderable Forces to oppoſe them, nor were able to maintain ſuch other Armies againſt them; yet when they were commanded, they did disband, without impoſing any condition at all upon the State.</p>
            <p>For the proceedings of this Parliament and their Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, I much more wonder how they can afford you any colour of juſtification; you knowing that we have a mixt Government in this Kingdom, conſiſting of three Eſtates, One of theſe (which was the King) withdraws himſelf from the Government, and raiſeth Forces without the conſent of the other two: whereupon both Houſes of Parliament (which are the other two Eſtates) carryes on the Government, and (having power ſo to do) judge the Kingdom to be in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and raiſe Forces for their defence, the defence of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to bring Delinquents to condign puniſhment,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114275:6"/>
then which, nothing can be more juſt. And upon this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and juſt quarrell, they raiſe ſeverall Armies, wherein were men of very great honour, power, and intereſt in the Kingdom; but (bleſſed be God) never any of their Armies (except what hath been done by you) did refuſe (that ever I heard of) to obey, when the Parliament (for the good and eaſe of the Kingdom, nay, although it were to lay them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and raiſe others in their room) commanded them to disband. And how any thing in this caſe reacheth to juſtifie the acting of an Army againſt that power that raiſed them, and ſhould command them, I know not.</p>
            <p>For thoſe inſtances of the Souldiers holding the hands of the Generall, when he would turn his Canon againſt his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and the Seamen the hands of the Pilot, who willingly runs the Ship upon a Rock; I muſt ſay, That in thoſe and ſuch like caſes of ſurprizall or extremity, where there is none to judge, nor no time or place for judgement, the danger being eminent, and the evil intention evident, the Law of Nature doth teach and juſtifie oppoſition to the unjuſt and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous power of Superiors: but it is no ground for a Rule where a judgement may be had, or expected, as now in the caſe betwixt the Parliament and Army. Theſe inſtances might have been more colourably to the Point, if the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament had drawn out Forces againſt the Army, to have cut them off; then, notwithſtanding the obedience they owe to the Parliament, they might poſſibly have defended them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt ſuch Force: But if the matter of Fact be truly ſtated, it will be far from your purpoſe; for the Army ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced upon the Parliament when they had not drawn out any Force at all againſt them. And that is much liker the Souldier turning the Canon, or drawing his Sword upon the Generall, for which I never yet heard of any juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>For the laſt thing alledged (although it be very darkly expreſſed, yet as underſtand the Argument) That the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies proceedings may be juſtified, when againſt injuſtice, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, and miſcarriage in Government: If that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114275:6"/>
were granted, and the Parliament were guilty in all, (which I am moſt confident can never be made good by clear in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, that they are guilty of any courſe of injuſtice or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, though all the world and the accuſer of the brethren to help, ſhould ſet about it,) yet that would not come up to juſtification of the Army, becauſe God hath not made them Judges for the people of the Kingdom, either of Juſtice or Injuſtice, right or wrong; Nor is the judgement of the whole Army equivolent to the Sentence of the meaneſt Judge in the Land, much leſſe to the judgement of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherein both the Army and all the people of the Kingdom are repreſented, therefore the people are not to account any thing unjuſt, unrighteous, or amiſſe in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, becauſe the Army hath judged it ſo; but when they conceive any thing to be amiſſe, it is their duty to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent it to thoſe whom God hath appointed to the office and place of Judgement.</p>
            <p>But if the meaning of this laſt part of it be, That God hath made the former ſucceſſes and preſent power of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my a Teſtimony to its oppoſing the pretended injuſtice, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, and miſcarriage of Government, Then the <hi>Turk</hi> may have the ſame Argument to juſtifie his title to all he hath gotten in <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> But the Wiſe man teacheth otherwiſe, <hi>That no man knoweth love or hatred by all that is before them,</hi> Eccl. 9. 8.</p>
            <p>Having thus conſidered all that the Army hath offered to the world (that I can hear of) for the juſtification of their late actions, of which I muſt needs ſay, That the oftener I weigh it, the lighter I finde it, and therefore the more I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it, the leſſe I am ſatisfied: (Although the Declaration be offered in Print, by your ſelves, to judge or anſwer) Yet having heard that the particular deſires in it are before the one or both Houſes of Parliament, I ſhall not aſſume the boldneſſe to frame poſitive anſwers to any of them, or to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe my poor judgement what were fit to be done: And in generall (I may ſay) I have heard, That in many of the particulars, the Parliament have much more reaſon to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114275:7"/>
of the Army, then the Army of the Parliament.</p>
            <p>For that part concerning <hi>Ireland,</hi> If upon examination it doth appear, that the Houſes never offered any thing to the Army for the Service of <hi>Ireland,</hi> (though larger then to others that accepted the imploiment) but it was by ſome of the Army plotted againſt and oppoſed, and that your not dealing clearly therein (at the firſt when if they would have refuſed, there were others ready to undertake the Service) hath much indangered that Kingdom, eſpecially now that it is ſeconded with this diſtraction in the Army, which hinders all preparations and proceedings in that Service; then the Parliament hath cauſe to complain.</p>
            <p>For that part which concerns your demand for all the Souldiers in the Kingdom, if that be a thing you know is not in the power of the Parliament to do, it being conceived that all the Treaſure in the Kingdom would come far ſhort of preſent pay; and we ſee now that little leſſe will give ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: And that the conſequence of this (in hope to get a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rong party to your ſelves which would be your diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage if you mean Peace, becauſe the more you are, the leſſe able the Parliament will be to give ſatisfaction) muſt indan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the raiſing all the Souldiers of the Kingdom againſt the Parliament, and tear all to peeces in a horrid mutiny; then the Parliament hath cauſe to complain.</p>
            <p>For that part concerning the Members, If the Houſe of Commons have done much more to purge the Houſe and put their Members, to triall, then ever any did before them, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Committee eight or nine moneths ſince, to receive all complaints and accuſations againſt any Member of the Houſe, and this Committee commanded to ſit every <hi>Thurſday</hi> in the <hi>Exchequer-chamber,</hi> and this poſted up in the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent places about <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> that all might take notice of it, and accordingly the Committee did fit for ſeverall weeks and no complaint was brought. And if for thoſe that are unduly elected (wherein the Army and their party have by much (as I hear) been moſt guilty) the ancient and onely courſe in Parliament of examining them at a Committee of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114275:7"/>
priviledges, be ſtill obſerved, and they fit ſo often as the great buſineſſes of the Houſe will give leave: Then the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament have cauſe to complain of this Complaint.</p>
            <p>For that part which concerns the accuſing of Members of the Houſe of Commons, although I ſhould deſire that the charge might be received and heard, (which by the way may at leaſt be thought hard to be done by an Army, and they the accuſers, informers, witneſſes, and yet it appears not how far they will make themſelves Judges too, when it is their own caſe, in relation to thoſe Members whom they ſay are their enemies) they have put a hard judgement up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But if upon a generall accuſation, before any thing be proved, you would have them ſequeſtred from the Houſe, may you not by the ſame rule ſequeſter a hundred the next day after? and if the Houſe ſhould grant it, in the caſe of two or ten, were it not injuſtice to deny it for a hundred? And if ſomething in the matter of theſe accuſations ſhould be (as by your printed accuſation it appears to be) for things done, or ſpoken in the Houſe of Commons; then to admit it, were the utter overthrow of all free Parliaments in this Kingdom; where all things that are ſpoken, or done, are onely queſtionable by themſelves that ſee or hear them, and at the ſame time the offence is committed, (unleſſe the fact be then agreed upon, and it be referred to themſelves to queſtion afterwards by conſent of the Houſe) otherwiſe they themſelves cannot queſtion any ſuch things, though it were the next day; but in no caſe at all can be queſtioned by any without the Houſe; and if it were otherwiſe, no man would dare to ſpeak freely in Parliament, which muſt needs prove the ruine of the Kingdom; although I ſhall never plead to excuſe the offences of any, eſpecially of thoſe that are in publike Imployment. Yet if this appear to be the very engine whereby the Prerogative hath endeavoured, from time to time, to beat down Parliaments, then this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath great cauſe to complain that this Army ſhould make uſe of it.</p>
            <p>For that part which concerns the putting an end to this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114275:8"/>
Parliament, and the chooſing new ones; ſo ſoon as it can be done, I am moſt confident it would not onely be agreed too, but the greateſt part of the Houſe (eſpecially of thoſe who have fitten the longeſt) would account it the greateſt happineſſe that ever befell them; for although they have taken unwearied pains day and night, run the greateſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards, and ſuffered the moſt eminently in their eſtates of any people in the Kingdom, many of them to the ruine of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their families; yet their reward from ſome of thoſe for whom they have done and ſuffered all this, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but reproches, and ſeeking ſome weak grounds to faſt n falſe aſperſions upon them, As in that (which is moſt commonly ſpoken) <hi>That the Members of the Houſe of Commons have gotten much of the Kingdoms money to themſelves.</hi> I have made enquiry into this buſineſſe; I am confident that no Member of the Houſe hath had a penny out of any Taxation, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution, or Impoſition upon the Kindom: there are (it is true) ſome who have been eminent in their ſufferings, or ſervices, that have had money given them ariſing from ſome Delinquents Eſtates, as others have had in the like caſes that are no Members of the Houſes, and ſome very few have had Offices or Places beſtowed upon them. But this, I dare ſay, that, Divide the Houſe into twenty parts, and there is nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen of them that have not had a penny given them: and let all that hath been given to the Members be ſtrictly caſt up, and it will not appear that they have had ſo much amongſt them (except thoſe of them that have had pay as Souldiers) as ſo many Enſigns on foot, nor half ſo much as they ought to have had by the Laws of the Kingdom for their wages. And now the Houſes have taken from thoſe few Members of the Houſe of Commons (that had them) the benefit of all Offices, and Places, and Gifts, with a Reſolution, That they ſhall not have any thing given them, nor any reparations, untill all the Debts of the Kingdom be payed. Therefore the Members of the Houſe of Commons have more reaſon then the Army to deſire an end of this Parliament, that ſo they may be put into as good a Condition as other people of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114275:8"/>
Kingdom. Yet, why the Army ſhould make it a demand at this time, when by their own ſubſequent Propoſitions them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſeem to judge it cannot be done with ſafety: and now, before we have the Kings Reſolutions upon the Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whereby it might be known whether he would (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law in that behalf) joyn in ſuch an Act; or the Kingdom ſo ſetled, that it were in any meaſure fit for it: Why it ſhould now, I ſay, be demanded? I know not, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to make the people beleeve it were ſomething that would hardly be granted at another time.</p>
            <p>For that part which concerns freedom for Petitions, if when things have been fully and freely debated, and reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as prejudiciall to the Kingdom, if the people be incited to petition for the ſame things again and again upon no new grounds or reaſon, this were rather a licentiouſneſſe then a liberty of petitioning, ſeeing it is a fundamentall Rule, that the ſame Bill which is rejected in the Houſe of Commons, cannot be offered in the Houſe again during that Seſſion of Parliament.</p>
            <p>For that part which concerns the power of Committees and Deputies, as alſo that concerning the Accounts, and likewiſe that concerning the Act of Oblivion, and the reſt that follow, if it be (as I have heard) that the Parliament have taken effectuall courſe in ſome of thoſe things, and were conſidering of the reſt, before your Declaration, then they might well have been left out of your deſires and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints.</p>
            <p>What ever hath been ſaid of theſe particulars, I ſhould be glad that the Parliament would not ſtand upon any thing which might be ſpoken for their advantage, or your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage; but rather ſet about the doing and reſolving every thing as far as they could in conſcience and in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to give you ſatisfaction. And before you refuſe that ſatisfaction offered you from the Parliament that did raiſe you, and make you an Army, and by whoſe Commiſſion and Authority you do Act, ſeriouſly weigh theſe Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:114275:9"/>
            <p n="1">1. That to go on to diſobey the Parliament, or reſiſt them in their lawfull Commands, is to reſiſt the Ordinance of God: For as the Adminiſtration of the Word and Sacraments are in the band of Gods Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters <hi>Jure Divino;</hi> ſo the Adminiſtration of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Juſtice, Government and Rule, are in the hand of the Magiſtrate <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> unqueſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider that you have been charged already too much to uſurpe the Office of Miniſtery; and if you appear alſo to incroach upon the Office and Place of the Magiſtrate, you will much confirm men in their opinions of that, which is generally thought you make your deſigne, <hi>viz.</hi> To take away, and overthrow all Government, and leave the people to an unuſuall licentious libertie, and as a means to that end, not onely keep the power of the Sword in your own hands, but by the force of it to draw out of the Parliament, and all other Counſels and Judicatures in the Kingdom, thoſe who will not either for fear, or baſe ends act to that deſigne. And however I, and (it may be) ſome others may account this a Scandall, becauſe we beleeve ſome of the chief Officers have better Principles, yet, if it ſhould be confirmed by your actions, they are ſuch reall demonſtrations, that no man could beleeve otherwiſe notwithſtanding all profeſſions and proteſtations to the contrary.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider that if you let looſe the bands of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and you that are Officers by your own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114275:9"/>
(and it may be further) reach the Souldiers to diſobey the Parliament, that leſſon will ſerve to teach them likewiſe how to reſiſt their own Officers, and this you may take as a ſure Rule, That a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude will not long be ſervants to any deſigne, but within a while they will be Maſters of it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider, That ſuch things as require force to obtain them, can be kept no longer then they have force to maintain them, which keeping in a very few yeers would be the ruine and looſing of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Conſider the reproch that will come to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion if you continue your proceedings, (and not onely reproch) but the apparent hazard to all the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches in <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Conſider the infinite diſhonour that would come to the Army, although by force they ſhould be able to compaſſe all their deſires: That not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding your dutie, truſt, and ingagement to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>England,</hi> you, whom they have made choice of out of the whole Kingdom to bear Arms for their Defence, againſt all their enemies and oppoſers, And you that have accepted of that ingagement upon this Condition in your Commiſſions, <hi>To obſerve the Direction of both Houſes of Parliament;</hi> And you that they have made better proviſions for, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed more marks of honour and reſpect upon, then upon any Army that ever they had: I do onely repeat theſe things, hoping upon ſerious conſideration of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114275:10"/>
them, you who have appeared gallant men, will ſweetly and timely return to obedience, ſo that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I, nor any elſe, ſhall ever have occaſion to make ſuch application as would ſtain all your glory, Which is and ſhall be the moſt earneſt prayer of the Author.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:114275:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
